Manuel E. Gondra Manuscript Collection:
Calendar of the Manuel E. Gondra Manuscript Collection, The University of Texas Library, prepared by Carlos Eduardo Castañeda, University of Texas, and Jack Autrey Dabbs, AM College of Texas. México: Editorial Jus, 1952.
1531-1920
Gondra, Manuel, 1871-1927.
Benson Latin American Collection, The University of Texas at Austin
Official documents, manuscripts, and correspondence related to the history of South America, collected by Manuel Gondra, professor and President of Paraguay from 1911-1920. This page is Part Four of five in the electronic version of the calendar.
Arrangement
The electronic version of this calendar guide presents the papers chronologically and has been divided into five parts, of which the current page is Part IV. The other parts of the guide may be found through the links below:
Part I: Introduction and Sixteenth Century Documents
Part II: Seventeenth Century Documents
Part III: Eighteenth Century Documents (1700-1777)
Part IV: Eighteenth Century Documents (1778-1799)
Part V: Nineteenth Century Documents, Twentieth Century Documents, and Maps
Foreword to the Calendar, by Carlos Eduardo Castañeda
The complete Forward may be found in
Part I
of the electronic guide.
Index Terms
Author and Subject terms may be found in
Part I
of the electronic guide.
Other Finding Aid
A brief descriptive notice of the Manuel E. Gondra Collection was published by Carlos E. Castañeda and Jack Autrey Dabbs in the
Handbook of Latin American Studies, Cambridge, Mass.: Harvard University Press, 1941, pp. 505-517.
Calendar
- Eighteenth Century Documents (1778-1799)
  - 1527 Ceballos, Pedro de. [Carta a José de Gálvez sobre desalojo violento de los Portugueses de Igatimí durante cesación de hostilidades.] Buenos Aires, January 26, 1778. 3 l. 17 × 23 cm. Modern copy from AGI 122-5-11-B. (Box [MG 800])
  - 1528 _____. [Carta a José de Gálvez sobre la imposición de papel sellado en la Provincia del Paraguay.] Buenos Aires, January 26, 1778. 3 l. 17 × 23 cm. Modern copy from AGI 122-5-11-B. (Box [MG 845])
  - 1529 Melo de Portugal, Pedro. [Carta a S. M. sobre el estado de la reducción de Remolinos fundada en el Chaco por Agustín Fernando de Pinedo.] Asunción, February 10, 1778. 2 p. 22 × 33 cm. f. 18-19. Modern copy from unnamed source. (Box [MG 93g])
    Inconstancy of Indians; government of Pinedo.
  - 1530 _____. [Carta a José Gálvez sobre las fundaciones de Fernando de Pinedo en prevención de avances portugueses.] Asunción, February 14, 1778. 2 l. 17 × 23 cm. Modern copy from AGI 122-5-1-C. (Box [MG 796])
  - 1531 _____. [Carta a José de Gálvez en que acusa el recibo de la representación hecha por José Naude de la Bergeman contra el cura de Caazapá, Manuel Fernández.] Asunción, February 14, 1778. 2 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 16-17. Modern copy from AGI 124-1-16. (Box [MG 1090e])
  - 1532 _____. [Carta a José de Gálvez sobre el uso de papel sellado en el Paraguay.] Asunción, February 14, 1778. 1 l. 17 × 23 cm. Modern copy from AGI 123-1-15. (Box [MG 1550])
  - 1533 Román y Cabezales, José. [Oficio a la Junta Municipal sobre las intenciones de S. M. hacia el establecimiento de un colegio seminario.] Asunción, February 25, 1778. 7 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 145-151. Modern copy from AGI 123-5-9-A. (Box [MG 1718u])
    Reference to cedula issued at Madrid, August 27, 1776.
  - 1534 Machado, Francisco. [Informe de la Contaduría General sobre representaciones enviadas del Paraguay.] Madrid, February 26, 1778. 10 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 1-10. Modern copy from AGI 123-5-9, with two typewritten copies, each 6 p. 21.5 × 32 cm. Also another modern copy, 9 l. 17 × 23 cm. from AGI 122-3-21-F. (Box [MG 113a])
    Petition of Pinedo for Franciscan hospital; complaints against Pinedo; promotion to Presidency of Charcas; founding of Remolinos and Concepción; investigation of charges against Pinedo; José Marcos Vallejo.
  - 1535 Vega, José Manuel de la. Relación de los meritos exercicios literarios del Doctor Don José Matheo de Roman Cabezales y Najera.... Madrid, March 6, 1778. 11 l. 17 × 23 cm. Modern copy from AGI 123-6-4. (Box [MG 1546])
  - 1536 CONSEJO DE INDIAS. [Adhesión del fiscal al informe de Francisco Machado de 26 de febrero de 1778.] Madrid, March 9, 1778. 1 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 10-10v. Modern copy from AGI 123-5-9, with two typewritten copies, each 1 p. 21.5 × 32 cm. (Box [MG 113b])
    Machado's informe is No. 1534 (MG 113a).
  - 1537 Román y Cabezales, José. [Carta a S. M. en que da cuenta de que el gobernador Pinedo no era querido de los indios por sus crueldades.] Asunción, March 13, 1778. 7 l. 17 × 23 cm. Modern copy from AGI 124-1-3-F. (Box [MG 1677])
    Removal of Indians from the Chaco to Remolinos and Fort Agatapí; ill treatment of Cacique Tazurín; scruples of Don Bernardino Arias; improved policy of Melo de Portugal.
    Printed: MA IV, 54-59.
  - 1538 Melo de Portugal, Pedro. [Carta a S. M. sobre reducciones de los indios del Chaco.] Asunción, March 13, 1778. 4 p. 22 × 33 cm. f. 19-22. Modern copy from unnamed source, with a second copy from AGI 122-5-2, 6 l. 17 × 23 cm. Also a third copy, 6 l. 17 × 23 cm., from AGI 124-1-3. (Box [MG 93h])
    Settlement of town in district of Los Remolinos, with special privileges for colonists; administration of Agustín Fernando de Pinedo; Mocoví Caciques Amelcón and Nazurín; Indian attacks and damage; use of tithes from Guaraní missions for defense.
    Printed: MA IV, 49-53.
  - 1539 Ceballos, Pedro de. [Carta a José de Gálvez sobre el auxilio que deben dar los gobernadores en sus jurisdicciones respectivas a los demarcadores de límites.] Buenos Aires, March 31, 1778. 4 l. 17 × 23 cm. Modern copy from AGI 122-5-11-A. (Box [MG 799])
    Difficulty of determining frontiers; physical obstacles; situation in Montevideo (Río Grande), Paraguay, Chiquitos, Mojos, Río Ytenés, Madera, Amazonas, Orinoco; Portuguese deserters in Chachapoyas and Lima; Marqués de Casa Tilly, Pedro de Cárdenas, Diego de Alvear, Baltasar Mesía.
    Printed: MJL X, 214-215.
  - 1540 Melo de Portugal, Pedro. [Carta a José Román y Cabezales en que remite copia de la junta municipal de 23 de Marzo de 1778.] Asunción, April 10, 1778. 6 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 152-157. Modern copy from AGI 123-5-9-A. (Box [MG 1718v])
    The seminary project.
  - 1541 CONSEJO DE INDIAS. [Decreto que se pida del virrey de Buenos Aires para el Marqués de Valdelirios un informe sobre cargos hechos a Agustín Fernando de Pinedo.] Madrid? April 28, 1778. 2 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 10v-11. Modern copy from AGI 123-5-9, with two typewritten copies, each 1 p. 21.5 × 32 cm. (Box [MG 113c])
  - 1542 Cabrera, Francisco de. Informe del Tribunal de Cuentas [sobre establecimiento de nuevas reducciones en el Gran Chaco.] May 10, 1778. 5 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 5-9. Modern copy from AGI 123-6-1. (Box [MG 1558c])
    Praise for work of Francisco Gavino de Arias, Gerónimo Matorras, and Lorenzo Suárez de Cantilla[na].
  - 1543 Román y Cabezales, José. [Informe a S. M. sobre la necesidad de establecer un colegio seminario en Asunción.] Asunción, May 13, 1778. 18 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 51-68. Modern copy from AGI 123-5-9-A. (Box [MG 1718k])
    Difficulties in enforcing royal orders on the subject.
  - 1544 Melo de Portugal, Pedro. [Carta a José de Gálvez transmitiendo carta a S. M. sobre subsistencia del colegio seminario que se pretende establecer en Asunción.] Asunción, May 13, 1778. 8 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 15-22. Modern copy from AGI 123-5-9-A. (Box [MG 1718f])
    Request for money for the college. Includes also letter of Gálvez to Miguel de San Martín Cueto on pious works for the college. El Pardo, February 27, 1779.
  - 1545 CONSEJO DE INDIAS. [Oficios de la Contaduría, José de Gálvez, el Consejo, y el fiscal, sobre expediente relativo a colegio seminario en el Paraguay.] Madrid? May 13, 1778-August 31, 1779. 5 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 46-50. Modern copy from AGI 123-5-9-A. (Box [MG 1718j])
    Addressed to Miguel de San Martín Cueto; includes transmittal by Román y Cabezales, Asunción, May 13, 1778.
  - 1546 Pacheco, Dr. Vista fiscal [sobre establecer a los indios del gran Chaco en las reducciones que promovió Gerónimo Matorras.] Buenos Aires, May 16, 1778. 4 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 9-12. Modern copy from AGI 123-6-1. (Box [MG 1558d])
    Pacification of Mocovís; administration of Agustín de Pinedo.
  - 1547 Castilla, José de. [Respuesta del fiscal de la Audiencia de la Plata relativa al fomento de un seminario en Paraguay.] La Plata, May 16, 1778. 2 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 4-5. Modern copy from AGI 123-5-9, with two typewritten copies, each 2 p. 21.5 × 32 cm. (Box [MG 312b])
    Includes transmittal by Audiencia de Charcas, La Plata, May 16, 1778.
  - 1548 Guinios, Manuel de. En 20 de Mayo de 1778 informa... á D. José de Gálvez los gravísimos perjuicios que al reino del Perú va a ocasionar la creación de el la Plata. 3 l. 17 × 23 cm. Modern copy from AGI 110-1-16. (Box [MG 1057])
    Boundaries of provinces.
  - 1549 Castilla, José de. Respuesta del Señor Fiscal [sobre fundación de universidad en Asunción y otros autos.] La Plata, May 27, 1778. 5 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 5-9. Modern copy from AGI 123-5-9, with two typewritten copies, each 2 p. 21.5 × 32 cm. (Box [MG 312c])
    Attention to conferring of degrees. Includes also transmittal to the court by the Audiencia de Charcas, May 27, 1778 and June 17, 1778.
  - 1550 Pacheco, Dr. [Vista fiscal sobre las dificultades que impiden el establecicimiento de nuevas reducciones en el Chaco.] Buenos Aires, June 2, 1778. 3 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 12v-14. Modern copy from AGI 123-6-1. (Box [MG 1558e])
    Gerónimo Matorras and Lorenzo Suárez de Cantillana; bellicose nature of Indians.
  - 1551 Ceballos, Pedro de? [Decreto que se proceda sin dilación al establecimiento de reducciones en el Chaco.] Buenos Aires, June 3, 1778. 6 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 14v-19. Modern copy from AGI 123-6-1. (Box [MG 1558f])
    Efforts of Lorenzo Suárez de Cantillana, Antonio Lapa, Francisco Gabino de Arias, and Pedro Antonio Araoz.
  - 1552 CONSEJO DE INDIAS? [Carta a Agustín Fernando de Pinedo comunicando aprobación real sobre toma de la Plaza de Igatimí.] Aranjuez, June 3, 1778. 2 l. 17 × 23 cm. Modern copy from AGI 125-4-17-B, with two typewritten copies, each 1 p. 21.5 × 32 cm. (Box [MG 179])
  - 1553 Román y Cabezales, José. [Carta a S. M. en que informa sobre conveniencia de establecer universidad en Asunción.] Asunción, June 13, 1778. 8 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 1-8. Modern copy from AGI 123-5-9, with two typewritten copies, each 4 p. 21.5 × 32 cm. (Box [MG 327a])
    Practical considerations; curricula of proposed university.
  - 1554 Machado, Francisco. [Expediente sobre la fundación de un colegio de Propaganda fide de franciscanos en la Provincia del Paraguay...con aprobación fiscal de 15 de julio de 1778 y resolución que se pase el expediente al Marqués de Valdelirios para que informe, 29 de julio de 1778.] Madrid, June 22, 1778. 2 l. 17 × 23 cm. Modern copy from AGI 123-5-17-C, with two typewritten copies, each 4 p. 21.5 × 32 cm. (Box [MG 156])
  - 1555 Carlos III. [Real cédula] al Cavildo cecular de la Ciudad de la Asuncion... que informe si combendra incorporar á la Corona Encomiendas de Indios de aquella Provincia. Aranjuez, June 22, 1778. 2 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 62v-63. Modern copy from AGI 123-1-15. (Box [MG 560b])
  - 1556 Pinedo, Agustín Fernando de. [Declaración que da a Villa Real de la Concepción las tierras circumvecinas.] Asunción, June 25, 1778. 4 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 7-10. Modern copy from AGI 123-7-25-A, with two typewritten copies, each 3 p. 21.5 × 32 cm. (Box [MG 151c])
  - 1557 Lezcano, Juan Ángel de. Relacion jurada... al Cargo, y Data General de la Administracion de los... Pueblos [de los indios guaranís del Uruguay y Paraná.] Buenos Aires, July 1, 1778. 12 l. 17 × 23 cm. Modern copy from AGI 125-7-7-E. (Box [MG 567])
    Separate statistics given for each town.
  - 1558 CHARCAS, AUDIENCIA DE. [Carta a S. M. en que informa sobre conveniencia de fundar universidad en Asunción.] La Plata, July 12, 1778. 7 l. 17 × 23 cm. Modern copy from AGI 123-5-9, with two typewritten copies, each 4 p. 21.5 × 32 cm. (Box [MG 313])
    Signed: José de Casalla, Ambrosio de Benavides, and José López Lisper[guer].
  - 1559 CONSEJO DE INDIAS. [Vista del Fiscal sobre la carta de Pedro Melo de Portugal de 10 de febrero de 1778.] Madrid, July 13, 1778. 3 l. 17 × 23 cm. Modern copy from AGI 123-6-1. (Box [MG 1551])
    Establishment of reductions in the Gran Chaco; law enforcement in los Remolinos.
  - 1560 Melo de Portugal, Pedro. [Carta a S. M. sobre el estado de la provincia del Paraguay.] Asunción, July 13, 1778. 6 p. 22 × 33 cm. p. 22-27. Modern copy from unnamed source, with a second modern copy, 8 l. 17 × 23 cm., from AGI 124-1-3. (Box [MG 93i])
    Weakness of defenses; founding of Concepción; wilderness areas suitable for habitation; economic control by Montevideo and Santa Fe; Indian policy.
  - 1561 _____? [Carta a S. M. sobre la defensa de la provincia contra las invasiones de los indios infieles.] Asunción, July 13, 1778. 3 p. 22 × 33 cm. p. 27-29. Modern copy from unnamed source. (Box [MG 93j])
    Antonio Ramos de la Vega; weakness of militia.
  - 1562 GUERRA, JUNTA DE. [Cumplimiento de la orden del Virrey Juan José de Vértiz, con fecha de 22 de Agosto de 1778.] Santísima Trinidad, August 24, 1778. 8 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 4v-11. Modern copy from AGI 124-1-15. (Box [MG 1089b])
    Text of order of Vértiz; protection against Indians by forts at Pergamino, La Esquina, and Melincué; organization of cavalry under Juan González; appointment of Juan Baez de Quiroga, Manuel Pinazo, Ventura Chavarría, Salvador Cabañas, and José Francisco Amigorena; order for formation of a Junta. Signed: Diego de Salas, Manuel de Pinazo, Ventura Echevarría, Salvador Cabañas y Ampuero, José Francisco de Amigorena, and Juan Baez de Quiroga.
  - 1563 Valdelirios, Marqués de. [Dictamen sobre el expediente formado por Agustín Fernando de Pinedo relativo a fundación de un colegio de Propaganda Fide en Asunción y resolución del Consejo que consulten entre sí el obispo y el gobernador.] Madrd, August 31-September 5, 1778. 13 l. 17 × 23 cm. Modern copy from AGI 123-5-17-C, with two typewritten copies, each 7 p. 21.5 × 32 cm. (Box [MG 1912])
    Request for new informes.
  - 1564 Carlos III. [Cédula real a Pedro Melo de Portugal que haga informe sobre fundación de un colegio y conferencíe con el obispo de Buenos Aires.] Madrid? September 5, 1778. 4 l. 17 × 23 cm. Modern copy from AGI 123-5-17-B, with two typewritten copies, each 3 p. 21.5 × 32 cm. (Box [MG 1903])
    Successful functioning of similar schools in Villa de Tarija, Ocopa, and Popayán.
  - 1565 GUERRA, JUNTA DE. [Junta de capitanes de todas las provincias del virreinato en que se considera un plan para combatir a los indios.] Santísima Trinidad, September 10, 1778. 21 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 11v-31. Modern copy from AGI 124-1-15. (Box [MG 1089c])
    Signed: Diego de Salas, Manuel de Pinazo, Ventura Echavarría, Salvador Cabañas y Ampuero, José Vague, and Juan Antonio Hernández.
  - 1566 Carlos III. [Cédula real al cabildo de Asunción sobre las denuncias hechas contra el Gobernador Pinedo.] San Ildefonso, September 18, 1778. 1 l. 17 × 23 cm. Modern copy from AGI 123-5-9, with two typewritten copies, each 1 p. 21.5 × 32 cm. (Box [MG 117])
  - 1567 CONSEJO DE INDIAS. Dictamen del Señor Fiscal [sobre demora necesaria en lo de la universidad hasta recibir informe de la Real Audiencia de Charcas.] Madrid, October 29, 1778. 2 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 8v-9. Modern copy from AGI 123-5-9, with two typewritten copies, each 1 p. 21.5 × 32 cm. (Box [MG 327b])
  - 1568 Ceballos, Pedro de. [Carta a José de Gálvez sobre la ocupación de Igatimí por los portugueses.] Buenos Aires, November 28, 1778. 3 l. 17 × 23 cm. Modern copy from AGI 125-4-17-A. (Box [MG 1656])
  - 1569 Vértiz, Juan José de. El Virrey de Buenos Aires documenta los motibos porque ha suspendido la entrada general á los indios hasta resolución de S. M. Buenos Aires, November 30, 1778. 4 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 1-4. Modern copy from AGI 124-1-15. (Box [MG 1089a])
  - 1570 Gallarreta, Pedro de. [Informe para la Contaduría General sobre la explotación de mina de azogue en la Provincia del Paraguay.] Madrid, December 5, 1778. 3 l. 17 × 23 cm. Modern copy from AGI 123-5-8-B. (Box [MG 757])
  - 1571 Melo de Portugal, Pedro. [Carta a S. M. que se nombre prelado al Dr. Antonio de Otazú, Paraguayo, canónigo de Arequipa.] Asunción, December 13, 1778. 3 l. 17 × 23 cm. Modern copy from AGI 123-5-8-A. (Box [MG 756])
  - 1572 CONTADURÍA GENERAL. [Informe que manifiesta el estado de los indios de las reducciones del Chaco y Tucumán.] Madrid, December 17, 1778. 7 l. 17 × 23 cm. Modern copy from AGI 123-6-1. (Box [MG 2086])
    Abstracts of pertinent documents, 1774-1777.
  - 1573 Carlos III? [Real Cédula que se siga tomando informes reservados sobre denuncias de mala conducta del Gobernador Pinedo.] 1778? 2 l. 17 × 23 cm. Modern copy from AGI 124-1-3-A. (Box [MG 1685])
  - 1574 _____. [Cédula real sobre creación de los Gobiernos de Mojos y Chiquitos.] Madrid? 1778? 4 l. 17 × 23 cm. Modern copy from AGI 120-7-27-F. (Box [MG 774])
    Presence of Portuguese near Santa Cruz and Tarija; their occupancy of Mato Grosso and Cuyabá.
  - 1575 BUENOS AIRES. Nota de las Intendencias establecidas en el Virreynato de Buenos Ayres, y Jurisdicciones respectivas que comprehenden. Buenos Aires? 1778. 2 l. 17 × 23 cm. Modern copy from AGI 124-3-22. (Box [MG 1104])
  - 1576 Suárez de Cantillana, Lorenzo. [Memorial al Virrey para la fundación de las reducciones de infieles que habitan el gran Chaco.] Buenos Aires? 1778? 2 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 19-20. Modern copy from AGI 123-6-1. (Box [MG 1558g])
    Approval of Juan José Vértiz.
  - 1577 Cabrera, Francisco de. Estado que manifiesta Valores producidos en este año por todos los Ramos de Rl. Hacienda... con distinción de los gastos causados en su Administracion... Año de 1778. 1 l. 23 × 34 cm. Modern copy from AGI 124-3-23. (Box [MG 1841])
  - 1578 Carlos III. [Real Cédula a la Audiencia de la Plata otorgando licencia para fundar una universidad en Asunción.] 1778? 5 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 1-5. Modern copy from AGI 123-5-9. (Box [MG 328a])
  - 1579 Melo de Portugal, Pedro. [Bando en que se propone castigar a los indios del Chaco.] Asunción, February 1, 1779. 1 p. 22 × 33 cm. Modern copy from V-22-1. (Box [MG 56])
  - 1580 CONSEJO DE INDIAS. [Dictamen fiscal sobre los informes de la Real Audiencia de Charcas y Gobernador del Paraguay relativos a fundación de una universidad en Asunción.] Madrid, March 6, 1779. 8 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 1-8. Modern copy from AGI 123-5-9, with two typewritten copies, each 4 p. 21.5 × 32 cm. (Box [MG 329a])
  - 1581 Carlos III. Minuta de Real Cédula al Virrey de Buenos Aires [ordenándose suspendan las entradas a los indios y se adelanten los fuertes.] El Pardo, March 15, 1779. 2 l. 17 × 23 cm. Modern copy from AGI 124-1-15. (Box [MG 1086])
    Concerning Pedro de Ceballos.
  - 1582 Mestre, Andrés. [Decreto del gobernador del Tucumán ordenando se forme una junta.] San Miguel del Tucumán, April 30, 1779. 3 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 20v-22. Modern copy from AGI 123-6-1. (Box [MG 1558h])
    Members: Lorenzo Suárez de Cantillana, Francisco Gabino Arías, José Molina, Pedro Antonio de Araoz, and Luis de Aguilar.
  - 1583 _____. [Decreto ordenando que se haga la marcha a la ciudad de Córdoba.] San Miguel del Tucumán, May 8, 1779. 2 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 22v-23. Modern copy from AGI 123-6-1. (Box [MG 1558i])
    Failure of Lorenzo Suárez de Cantillana to arrive; Francisco Gabino Arias to form junta in Mestre's absence.
  - 1584 ASUNCIÓN, CABILDO ECLESIÁSTICO DE. [Solicitud a S. M. se consigne el caudal del difunto obispo Juan José de Priego a la edificación de una nueva catedral.] May 8, 1779. 3 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 1-3. Modern copy from AGI 123-5-16-A, with two typewritten copies, each 2 p. 21.5 × 32 cm. (Box [MG 155a])
    Signed: Antonio Sánchez, Andrés Félix Quiñones, Antonio de la Peña, Pedro Zamudio, José Román y Cabezales, and José Lino de León.
  - 1585 ASUNCIÓN, CABILDO DE. [Certificación de la pobreza de la Iglesia Catedral y su ruinoso estado.] May 10, 1779. 3 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 3v-5. Modern copy from AGI 123-5-16-A, with two typewritten copies, each 2 p. 21.5 × 32 cm. (Box [MG 155b])
    Signed: Francisco Javier de Acevedo, Fernando Larios Galván, José Cañete, Bernardo de Haedo, Fermín de Arredondo y Lobatón, and José del Casal.
  - 1586 Melo de Portugal, Pedro. [Auto del gobernador de la provincia que se haga inspección de los templos de los regulares expulsos.] Asunción, May 12, 1779. 2 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 10-11. Modern copy from AGI 123-5-16-A, with two typewritten copies, each 2 p. 21.5 × 32 cm. (Box [MG 155e])
  - 1587 ASUNCIÓN, CABILDO ECLESIÁSTICO DE. [Solicitud a S. M. que valide el testamento del obispo Juan José Priego y Caro que deja esta iglesia heredera de sus bienes.] May 12, 1779. 2 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 6-7. Modern copy from AGI 123-5-16-A, with two typewritten copies, each 2 p. 21.5 × 32 cm. (Box [MG 155c])
  - 1588 Acevedo, Francisco Javier. [Nombramiento de García Rodríguez Francia y Francisco de las Llagas Cabañas para hacer reconocimientos de las iglesias.] Asunción, May 14, 1779. 1 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 11v. Modern copy from AGI 123-5-16-A, with two typewritten copies, each 1 p. 21.5 × 32 cm. (Box [MG 155f])
  - 1589 Alcántara Rodríguez, Pedro. [Certificación de los nombramientos hechos por Francisco Javier de Acevedo en esta fecha.] Asunción, May 14, 1779. 2 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 11v-12. Modern copy from AGI 123-5-16-A, with two typewritten copies, each 1 p. 21.5 × 32 cm. (Box [MG 155g])
  - 1590 Rodríguez Francia, García and Francisco de las Llagas Cabañas. [Informe sobre el estado deteriorado de la Santa Iglesia Catedral.] Asunción, May 14, 1779. 2 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 13-14. Modern copy from AGI 123-5-16-A, with two typewritten copies, each 2 p. 21.5 × 32 cm. (Box [MG 155i])
  - 1591 JUNTA REDUCCIONAL. [Acuerdo de la junta sobre las situaciones en que se deben formar las reducciones, su número, y presidios que las guarnezcan.] San Miguel del Tucumán, May 20, 1779. 8 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 23v-30. Modern copy from AGI 123-6-1. (Box [MG 1558j])
    Signed: Francisco Gabino Arias, Lorenzo Suárez de Cantillana, José de Molina, Pedro Antonio Araoz, and Luis de Aguilar.
  - 1592 _____. [Acuerdo sobre el gobierno espiritual que ha de regir las reducciones de esta provincia.] San Miguel del Tucumán, May 24, 1779. 3 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 30-32. Modern copy from AGI 123-6-1. (Box [MG 1558k])
  - 1593 _____. [Acuerdo en que nombran al gobernador como la persona para el arreglo y población de las reducciones.] San Miguel del Tucumán, May 26, 1779. 3 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 32v-34. Modern copy from AGI 123-6-1. (Box [MG 1558)
  - 1594 Rodríguez Alcántara, Pedro. [Certificación de la aceptación de nombramientos de García Rodríguez Francia y Francisco de las Llagas Cabañas, por Francisco Javier de Acevedo.] Asunción? May, 1779? 1 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 12v. Modern copy from AGI 123-5-16-A, with two typewritten copies, each 1 p. 21.5 × 32 cm. (Box [MG 155h])
  - 1595 JUNTA REDUCCIONAL. [Que se pase el presente Libro de Acuerdos al Procurador General para que exponga su sentir en los mismos términos.] San Miguel del Tucumán, June 2, 1779. 7 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 35-41. Modern copy from AGI 123-6-1. (Box [MG 1558m])
    Consideration of equipment and animals needed; need for artisans and soldiers; disagreement among the junta.
  - 1596 Fernández, Manuel Ignacio. [Carta a José de Gálvez sobre las peripecias de la fundación de Remolinos y la independencia del virrey que se muestra por el Ramo de Guerra del Paraguay.] Buenos Aires, June 8, 1779. 9 l. 17 × 23 cm. Modern copy from AGI 122-5-2. (Box [MG 1568])
    Pedro Melo de Portugal, José Martínez, Fulgencio Yegros, Carlos Morfi, and Agustín de Pinedo.